A Guide to the Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- SERIES II. BOUND VOLUMES
  - Two letterbooks of Major J.C. Duane, Chief Engineer, Army of the Potomac; A ledger letterbook contains copies of letters sent and received by Duane in his official capacity, 1864 July 3-1865 June 15. 1864 May-1865 Jun (Box 10)
    A small pocket letterbook contains carbon copies of Duane's dispatches sent on the letter head of the Army of the Potomac headquarters 1864 March 11-July 29. A small pocket in the back of the volume contains loose dispatches received March and April 1865 together with carbon sheets, an ivory pencil, and a mss map of Hatcher's Run, 1865 April 1. Correspondents included J. G. Barnard, Richard Delafield, Winfield Scott Hancock, A. A. Humphreys, Rufus Ingalls, George G. Meade, Ira Spaulding, Gouveneur Kemble Warren, Horatio G. Wright. #1182
  - Two Diaries of William F. Hunter 1862-1863 (Box 10)
    Describing camp life and troop movements, the effects of marching on his health, constant rain, skirmishes, capture of Confederates, the Battle of Perryville, Don Carlos Buell, Thomas L. Crittenden, William S. Rosecrans, capture of Morgan's men at McMinnville, Tennessee, Battle of Stone's River/Murfreesboro, pay, destruction of Confederate flour mills, and many other references which can be found in the Virgo record. #10547-bm
  - Diary of Thomas S. Mercer, Cedar Park, Maryland, a tobacco planter 1857-1858 (Box 10)
    Writing about farm routine, servants, insect devastation, the weather, family activities, and trips to Washington and Baltimore. #5702
  - Four Memoranda on the Conduct of the War in Virginia and the Carolinas, etc. by Richard Oswald 1779-1781, In a red binder (Box 10)
    Because of his acquaintance with many of the leading American colonists, he was frequently consulted during the war by the English ministry; #703
  - Zea y de la guerra, Fuerza Militar de los Estados Unidos Manuscript, 66 pages, and Zea y de la guerra, Memoria sobre la Guerra Civil de los Estados Unidos de America Manuscript, 36 pages, by Lt. Col. Pedro, a military attache of the Spanish Legation in Washington, D.C. 1865-1866, 2 bound vol. (Box 11)
    Discussing the re-election of Abraham Lincoln, troop strengths on both sides, deserter problem, demobilization of the Federal armies, the formation of 5 military districts in the South, the sale of "war surplus materials," the policy of President Johnson, problems raised by the liberation of slaves, the operation of the Freedmen's Bureau, transfer of troops to the Mexican border and the possibility of U.S. intervention in European affairs. #7231
  - Dispatch Book of General Alfred Pleasonton, Union general 1862 Oct-Nov (Box 11)
    Kept while commanding the cavalry corps at South Mountain, Antietam, and Fredericksburg. The dispatches are addressed to Generals Randolph Barnes Marcy and John Grubb Parke. #495
  - Treatise by William Sanderson on the necessity of creating an office in the government of Great Britain to handle foreign exchange 1622 Apr 8 (Box 11)
    #4577
  - Virginia Militia Order Book 1775-1780 (Box 11)
    Kept chiefly by Joseph Jones and containing records of court-martials and orders of General Muhlenberg and Baron Von Steuben. #993
  - "De Kissimmee au Golfe de Mexique" by John Watson, illustrated with drawings and photographs 1892 (Box 11)
    Describing a sailing voyage through central Florida from Orlando to Punta Gorda. #6173
- SERIES III: SLIPCASE COLLECTIONS
  - Cotton Mather to the Rev. Benjamin Colman, in brown slipcase 1716 Feb 1, ALS, 3p. (Othertype 1)
  - "Savagery," with corrections and changes by Henry Major Tomlinson, in blue slipcase n.d., AMsS, 10p. (Othertype 2)
    #38737
  - Answer of the Elders of the Several Churches in New England to two and thirty questions by Richard Mather 1638-1639, AMs, 49p., in green slipcase (Othertype 3)
  - Cotton Mather to Dr. Bartholomaeus Ziegenbalg, including a portion of the manuscript of India Christiana(1712) in original Latin, with TLS, 1916 Jun 3 and a translation by Dr. Samuel B. Platner, in brown mottled slipcase 1717 Dec 31, ALS, 12p. (Othertype 4)
  - Funeral Sermons preached by Richard Mather for Mr. Toogood, 4p., and "Goodwife" Wilkins, 7p. 1648, 2AMs, 11p., in maroon slipcase (Othertype 5)
  - Incomplete ordination sermon preached by Richard Mather at "Marleborough,"on Hebrews 13:17 1659 Apr 7, AMs, 16p., in maroon slipcase (Othertype 6)
  - Sermons by Increase Mather 1698, 5 AMs, 23p., in green slipcase (Othertype 7)
  - Notes for a Sermon by Cotton Mather on Psalm 2.6 entitled "Christ is a King" 1704 Jul 16, AMs, 8p.,in a red slipcase (Othertype 8)
    #4859
  - Diary for Cotton Mather for 1712 1712, AMs, 124p., in blue slipcase (Othertype 9)
  - Sermon by Increase Mather preached at the ordination of T. Walker 1718 Oct 29, AMs, 2p., in maroon slipcase (Othertype 10)
  - "Concerning Apparitions," Chapter 7 of Remarkable Providences, with marginal notes in the hand of Increase Mather [1684?], AMs, 10p., in blue slipcase (Othertype 11)
  - Paterna n.d., bound AMs, in brown slipcase (Othertype 12)
    Contains an account of the life of Cotton Mather written for his son, in his own handwriting. #3860
  - Manuscript Notebook kept by John Minott of Dorchester on sermons by Richard Mather, Williams, Stoughton, and others 1663-1664, AMs, 308p., in blue slipcase (Othertype 13)
  - Manuscript Notebook kept by Edward Bromfield 1682, AMs, in blue slipcase (Othertype 14)
  - Manuscript Notebook on Sermons kept by Joseph Baxter of Medfield 1690-1693, AMs, in blue slipcase (Othertype 15)
  - Walt Whitman "On Shakespeare and Ben Johnson," with typed transcript ca. 1850, AMs, 1p., in black & white cover (Othertype 16)
  - Walt Whitman, "On Samuel Johnson," with typed transcript [1857], AMs, 1p., in a half brown levant morocco cover (Othertype 17)
  - Walt Whitman, "On Shakespeare and His Sonnets and Edmund Spenser," with typed transcript [1850], AMs, 1p., in white & green cover (Othertype 18)
  - Walt Whitman, "Homer and Shakespeare. A Comparison," with typed transcript [1857], AMs, 1p., in green & brown cover (Othertype 19)
  - Walt Whitman "Abraham Lincoln, A Glint Inside of His Cabinet on the Appointment of Mr. [James] Harlan as Secretary of the Interior," incomplete, with typed transcript [1865], AMs, 2p., in blue & green cover (Othertype 20)
  - Commonplace book of William Strachey, historian and first secretary of the Virginia Colony ca. 1615-1630, AMs, in red slipcase (Othertype 21)
    The Commonplace book was begun after his return to England and there are no mentions of Virginia. Strachey has numbered this volume throughout, arranging his private thoughts and references to books alphabetically. # 1123
  - Letters from Edward Everett Hale to Mr. Poore re New England antiquities; to Mrs. Mary [Gideon Hiram] Hollister re a play about Thomas a Becket; to Mr. Benjamin re Veiled Prophet; and to Mr. Ban 1876-1901, 6 ALS & ANS, in a brown slipcase (Othertype 22)
    #38-736
  - Autograph Manuscripts and Notes by John Burroughs used in or prepared for Indoor Studies and Fresh Fields; containing the following pieces: Arnold's View of Emerson & Carlyle, 20 p.; A Sunday in Cheyne Row, 23p.; and notes on Carlyle as a Critic, 7 p.; Emerson, 9 p.; and Matthew Arnold, 13p. & 10 p. n.d., AMsS, in orange slipcase (Othertype 23)
  - "The Life of Thomas Reade, Rector of Moreton, in the County of Dorset, Written by his Own Hand and Designed to be Continued by Him, as Long as God Wills It" 1692, AMs, 47p., in a small brown leather binding, with a genealogical table of the Reade family and a small sketch of their coat of arms at the end, burgundy slipcase (Othertype 24)
    Containing an detailed account of his travels to Newfoundland and the Colony of Virginia. Reade (1657-1723) began his account of his first voyage in 1674, when he sailed as a physician and surgeon in chief, on a merchant vessel commanded by Captain Stoplen Pain. He furnishes much information about the fishing trade, crops, planters, diseases, flora and natural features of Newfoundland.
    He undertook another voyage with Captain Sampson Clark in the Royal Exchange to the Cape Verde Islands, "Terra Nova," Spain and Italy. Other voyages followed with Captain Fastolf on the Thomas and Francis, Captain James Cuttiford on the Real Friendship, Captain Wootten on the Mercy, and Captain Erastus Joy for the Virginia Colony where he stayed with the Colonel Leroy Griffin. While discussing his stay in Virginia, he mentions the tobacco industry, flora, diseases, especially the effects of rattlesnake bite and the habits and characteristics of the snake, much about the native Indians, Jamestown, and treatment of indentured servants.
    His account continues with his return to England, his studies, entry into holy orders, his marriage to Joanna Woodward, and the birth of his children. # 7290
  - Travels in America, 1806-1809: The Journal of Alexander Dick 1806-1809, AMs, 306p., used in a blue slipcase (Othertype 25)
    Kept by Dick while on a mission to the United States by the Commissioners under the British Convention of 1806 to investigate various claims which Parliament had undertaken to settle. He left Edinburgh on August 1806, and sailed from Liverpool in November.
    The journal covers visits to New York, Trenton, Princeton, Philadelphia, Baltimore, Georgetown, Alexandria, Washington, D.C., where he met both Thomas Jefferson and James Madison and other prominent Americans, Hanover, Gettysburg, Frederic, Norfolk, Petersburg, Richmond, Charlottesville, where he visited Monticello, Warm Springs, Warrenton, Raleigh, Fayetteville, Charleston, Wilmington, returning home from Halifax via Washington and Philadelphia. #4528
  - Journal of Travels in the western United States kept by John Scanland 1817, AMs, in a blue slipcase. (Othertype 26)
    Scanland's journal gives his observations on western Virginia, Kentucky, Indiana, Illinois and Missouri. He comments on the scenery, towns, inns and innkeepers, the state of agriculture and the suitability of land for farming, and the people he meets, particularly noting their health, social condition, and general state of cleanliness. He also reflects continually on his sweetheart back home, comparing her to a new girl he meets on his travels. Of interest is a brief description of a flood in Shawneetown, Ill. # 2458
  - Journal of "A Tour to the Northern States in the Summer of 1815 through Rhode Island, Connecticut, New York, New Jersey, and Pennsylvania" by [J] Wood 1815, AMs, in a blue slipcase. (Othertype 27)
    Wood makes observations on customs, institutions, intellectual life, weather and travel conditions, agriculture, and cotton textile manufacturing, and comments on the differences between northern and southern society including the general prosperity in the north and the high cost of free labor. Topics of interest include descriptions of New York City; a Fourth of July celebration; a fatal duel; a medical procedure; the casting of gudgeons; sermons he hears; national politics; sword, pistol, and woolen factories; views on female education particularly geography which enables women to "understand the conversation of men" and astronomy which will "lead the mind to its maker" and noting that "female pedantry is at all times abominable"; a murder trial; the purchase of cotton manufacturing machines; and medicinal uses of the slippery elm. People he meet include members of the Biddle family, a General Doughty, and Benjamin Silliman of Yale with whom he debates on "the difference of the mental qualities of the Negro and the white man." # 2503
  - Tobacco Letterbook kept by Robert Anderson 1698-1717, AMs, 153p., in a blue folding slipcase (Othertype 28)
    Anderson was a native of New Kent County, Virginia, presently Hanover County, who operated a store and a plantation, and served as a factor for several British merchants. Until 1700, Anderson was jointly concerned with Cuthbert Jones and Samuel Clarke, of England, in the operation of the store and in the purchasing of tobacco in Virginia. After 1700, Jones continued to consign European goods to Anderson and to order annual purchases of tobacco. Occasionally, John Page and Richard Lee also used Anderson as their factor. Anderson consigned his own tobacco harvests to Page, Lee, John Gibson, or John Lane. In 1713, he was appointed an executor in the estate of John Page, which brought him into association with Micajah and Richard Perry.
    All of these activities are reflected in his letters, as well as revealing information about the Virginia economy, annual tobacco prices, rates of exchange, shipping rates, annual crop conditions, store keeping, and his duties as a Virginia factor for British firms. The letterbook also contains a small group of letters, 1715-1717, pertaining to the executors settlement of his estate. # 4047
  - Manuscript Journal by Robert H. Fisher, of Suffolk, entitled Narrative of a Voyage to the West Indies, for the purpose of attempting the establishment of an ice market in the Island of Jamaica1800-1801, 136 p. (Othertype 29)
  - Prose and Verse by H.H.H, Stamford, Connecticut, inscribed to Mrs. James Wilcox, of Noroton Hill, Stamford, Connecticut 1869, AMsS, 80p., in red slipcase (Othertype 30)
    #38-739
  - "Souvenirs de' Amerique" Two bound volumes in the hand of Dorothea, Duchesse de Dino (later Duchesse de Sagan), the niece of Tallyrand 1840-1842, 2 AMs volumes, in light red slipcase (Othertype 31-32)
    Containing her transcriptions of letters by Louis Aime Adolphe Fourier de Becourt, with annotations by de Bacourt, originally written while he was French Minister in Washington. These letters narrate his daily life in Washington, and travels through the country. The second volume contains copies of printed sources describing the economy and society of the United States. # 9517
  - Journal of the Travels of William Hugh Grove in England, Flanders and America 1698-1732, AMsS, 81p., in red slipcase (Othertype 33)
    #3850
  - Student Notebook of Naval Tactics kept by C.H. Swasey while at the United States Naval Academy 1859, AMs, 281p., light red slipcase (Othertype 34)
    #10,066
  - Letterbook of the Company for Propagation of the Gospel in New England 1688-1761, AMs, 322p. (volume), brown slipcase (Othertype 35)
    #38-632-a
  - Typescript Abstract of the Letterbook of the Company for Propagation of the Gospel in New England, compiled as an aid for selling the original book. Tipped in is a letter, November 28, 1924, from Henry N. Stevens to William Gwinn Mather, inquiring whether he is interested in obtaining the volume 1688-1761, TMs, 30p., marbled cover (Othertype 36)
    #38-632-b
  - Virginia Orderly Books of the Virginia Militia Forces in the Defense of Norfolk during the War of 1812 against the piratical raids of Sir George Cockburn. 1813-1814, In light brown slipcase. (Othertype 37-38)
    The first orderly book is that of the artillery corps, from Winchester, and the first eleven pages were written by the commander Major James Faulkner with the remainder in the handwriting of his sergeants. It records the events of the march to Norfolk, the organization of the artillery under Colonel Read, and all the General, Brigade, and Regimental orders to June 17, 1813, when Major Faulkner was ordered to Craney Island. At the end is a note by Charles J. Faulkner about the finding of the book. The second orderly book was that of Elisha Boyd, Lt. Colonel of the 4th Regiment of Virginia Militia, and father-in-law of the first Charles James Faulkner, covering May 3 to August 1, 1814, when Washington was threatened by Cockburn and the defenses of Norfolk were strengthened. On July 22 an attack was repulsed and dead buried. It also records courts-martial, punishments, and all the general, brigade, and regimental orders. #38-728-a
  - Alexander Spotswood, Lt. Governor of Virginia, "Proposals for Leasing my Ironworks at Tuball with all that is now made use of to carry them on" 1739 Jul 20, AMsS, 4p., in blue slipcase. (Othertype 39)
    Describing thousands of acres of woodland, iron mines, slaves, cattle, his plant for making iron at a settlement called Spotswoodville, his manufacturing procedure, production rates, cost in labor and raw materials, and transportation opportunities. # 425
  - Board of Trade Manuscript volume, Whitehall 1721 Sep 8, AMs, 131p., in light red slipcase (Othertype 40)
    Containing the report of the commission to examine the state of the Plantations on the continent of America, signed by J. Chetwood, P. Dominique, Edward Ashe, and Martin Bladen, and including information on forms of government, population, militia strength and trade. Colonies surveyed in the report are Nova Scotia, New Hampshire, Massachusetts Bay, Rhode Island, Connecticut, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, and South Carolina. Other sections are entitled: Consequence of the Plantation trade, French Mississippi, Considerations for favoring improving and enlarging the dominions in America, in relation to the Indians, and in relation to the government of the Plantations. # 3636
  - Journals kept by Charles Joseph Losse de Bayac (1742- ) 1763-1783, 2 AMs, 181p. & 216p., in blue slipcases (Othertype 41, 42)
    He served in a regiment under Comte de Rochambeau's command during the French operations during the American Revolutionary War; a key to pages describing various events can be found under the accession number of the collection.
    The first volume covers the period 1763-1779, is not based on first hand observations and is largely derivative. It includes a summary of events leading up to the outbreak of hostilities in 1775; Bunker Hill; Ticonderoga, Montreal, and the attack against Quebec; operations in Virginia and the Carolinas; evacuation of Boston; Declaration of Independence; New York and New Jersey campaigns; the Northern lakes; British occupation of Philadelphia; Pennsylvania campaigns in 1777; Connecticut and New York in 1777; Pennsylvania & New Jersey in 1777-1778; Burgoyne Campaign; British evacuation of Philadelphia; and the arrival of D'Estaign.
    The second volume covers the period 1780 June to 1783 June and is based upon first hand observation offering an authoritative account of French military and naval operations during the Revolution. It includes the voyage from France, arrival in Rhode Island; Camp at Philipsburg and junction with Americans under George Washington; crossing of the Hudson and march to Philadelphia; march south to Yorktown, Virginia; Yorktown Campaign and subsequent British surrender; Winter quarters; account of Rodney's victory over De Grasse on April 12, 1782; march north to Boston; Embarkation and voyage home via Porto Rico and Porto Bello; arrival at Brest; description of the Dunkard settlement at the Ephrata Cloisters; and remarks re the Quakers. # 4976
  - Charles Lloyd, Jr. to Bernard Barton 1821-1824, 18 ALS, in blue slipcase (Othertype 43)
    Lloyd discusses his poetry, translations, and publication problems, criticizes Barton's poetry and comments on Robert Southey, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Lord Byron, John Keats, Charles Lamb, and P.M. James, and mentions his family, home, and frequent bouts of depression; includes two letters from his father, Charles Lloyd, Sr. to Barton and a manuscript, "Stanzas on the Death of Caroline Queen of Great Britain. For listing of individual letters see the guide. #38-733
  - Robert Louis Stevenson to his father, Thomas Stevenson 1872-1886, 6 ALS, in green slipcase (Othertype 44)
    Writes describing his new lodgings, a fire in Sachsenhauser, and mentioning Sir Walter Simpson (1872 Aug 4); acknowledges authorship of "Harold" and "Salt Water Financier" and will be home soon from [France?] [1878?]; though working hard, feels like he must produce until death, and has gotten two editions of Arabian Nights (1883 Jun 15); sends revisions for his father's paper read as President of Royal Society of Edinburgh and mentions his opinion of Thomas Carlyle (1885 Jan 14); discusses problems with David in Kidnapped and mentions "Alan Breck" (1886 Apr or May); and believes Kidnapped is going to succeed (1886 Jul 28). #38-730
  - Edward Fitzgerald to Bernard Barton 1837-1848, 74 ALS, 5 AMs (Othertype 45)
    Fitzgerald writes about his travels in England and Ireland, his family, art collecting, especially his interest in John Constable, and his friends, particularly Alfred Tennyson and Thomas Carlyle. He also mentions Edward Moxon, Leigh Hunt, William Wordsworth, John Henry Newman, Maria Edgeworth, George Peacock, Samuel Lawrence, George Crabbe, Thomas de Quincey, Charles Dickens, and William Makepeace Thackery.
    In addition to the 74 letters to Barton, are Fitzgerald's copies of and commentaries on the Biblical stories of Joseph, David, Saul, and Jonathan, copies of two poems by Tennyson, a registered letter receipt, and five letters from John Gibson Lockhart & Charlotte Sophia (Scott) Lockhart to Barton. #38-731
  - Joseph Conrad letters to Arthur Symons 1909-1921, 15 ALS (Othertype 46)
  - "Treatise on Florida and Louisiana" by Thomas Rodney (1744- 1811), member of the Continental Congress and judge for the Mississippi Territory 1810, AMs, 15p., with typescript, in red slipcase (Othertype 47)
    Concerning the exploration and title to East and West Florida and Louisiana, the Spanish and French Colonies in America, and the Louisiana Purchase; he discusses whether the United States has a well-founded claim to West Florida, whether the people of West Florida were justified in declaring themselves independent, and if the United States would be justified in defending West Florida or in adding it to the Union. # 5178
  - James Monroe Letters to Judge Robert Morris, [Dr. Janney?], Dr. Charles Everett, and unidentified correspondents 1794-1829, 10 ALS, in green leather binding (Othertype 48)
    Discusses the different types of stock in the United States, available at various rates of interest (1806 Dec 25); lands in New Jersey from the estate of L. [Kortright?] (1794 Apr 1); the illness of President James Madison (1813 Jun 28); belief that his political documents and letters will vindicate his conduct both before his mission to Europe and since his return home (1816 Jan 24); illness of Mrs. Monroe (1820 Jul 1; 1824 Sep 1); upcoming visit of the Marquis de Lafayette (1824 Sep 1); invitation to dine with Judge Nelson and James Monroe at Mr. Michie's, (1828 Jul 26). # 2528
  - Letters of James Monroe to Stephen Pleasonton 1811-1831, 33 ALS & TLS, in blue slipcase (Othertype 49)
    Chiefly concerning matters pertaining to the running of the Department of State in his absence, and one letter to Samuel Pleasonton, as clerk in the Department of State; and one letter to General John Mason.